Hi, everyone. Welcome to the 11th
lecture of 6 .006, our first lecture
on weighted shortest paths. Until now,
we've only been talking about graphs where
we measure distance
in terms of the number
of edges in a path.
Today, we're going to generalize that notion, but I just want
to go over what we've talked about in the last two lectures.
In the last two lectures, we've talked about two
algorithms, breadth -first search and depth -first search,
to solve a range of problems. Here's some of the problems
that we've been solving. Single -source shortest paths,
where distances are measured
in number of edges in a path.
And we use
BFS to solve this problem, starting from a
single source, usually a vertex S that we call.
And we solve that in
linear time. We solve that in
order v plus e.
That's what we called
linear time for a graph.
For the special case of
single -source reachability,
here we had to return a shortest
path distance for every vertex.
And there was at most e things reachable from a
vertex. So this is the bound we got. But in the
special case for single -source reachability, when our output
only has to list the vertices that are reachable from me,
the number of things reachable in basically a spanning tree of
the connected component of my source can almost be of order e.
And so for all the little
singleton vertices in my graph,
I don't really care.
So I can get this in order e. But
that's kind of a little optimization.
The next thing we did was we
talked about connected components.
And we didn't just reduce
to using a search algorithm
like a single -source reachability
algorithm like BFS or DFS.
We put a for loop around that to explore the entire graph by
basically saying, if I've explored one connected component,
then I can look at any other vertex I haven't seen
and explore the next one. And so that actually, with
a little analysis, also got linear time because I'm
at most traversing any component of my graph once.
That's kind of the idea.
And we can use that using BFS or DFS, really, because we're just
trying to get a thing that searches an entire connected component.
And then this topological sort we did at the end of the last lecture,
we used full DFS to give an ordering of the vertices in a DAG.
Maybe I'll specify clearly
that this is only for a DAG,
where we have an ordering of the vertices so all
the edges go forward in that order, for example.
And that we also
did in linear time.
An integer associated with that
edge. It's going to be called a weight.
So here's an example of a weighted graph G. And I've labeled in red weights
for each of these edges. There's a directed graph on eight vertices.
And I've got a integer associated with each edge.
You'll notice some of them are positive. Some of
them are negative. It's OK to be 0 as well.
It's just any integer edge weight here.
So generally, we're going to be, along with our
graph G, we're going to be given a weight function
that maps the edges of G to,
we're going to say, integers.
In this class, anyway.
In other contexts, in mathematics, you might have this be real
numbers. But in this class, we're going to deal with integers.
So each edge, if
you have an edge,
we're going to say this is the
weight of this edge E from E.
We might sometimes,
if this edge E is uv,
we might sometimes say
the weight from u to v,
since we have a simple
graph that's unambiguous.
But this is just talking about our notation. So in general, for example,
the weight from vertex B to F in this graph is what? Can someone tell me?
Minus 4. JASON KUO - Minus 4,
right? It's right here. And I'll
be consistent with my coloring
because I've got
colored chalk today.
Minus 4, happiness.
All right,
so why do we care about
adding weights to our graph?
Well, this comes up a lot in many applications.
For example, distance isn't a road network, right?
Here,
so from Mass Ave,
front of MIT, to Central Square,
we might think of that as one road.
Maybe you've got each road is a connection
between two intersections in my road network.
But an edge, it takes
longer to go from,
say, Vassar Street to Amherst. That takes a shorter amount of
time than it does to go from Memorial Drive across the river
to Beacon Street, right?
So we might want to associate a larger distance
or a weight associated with that edge, right?
Latency in a network, for example. Maybe strength
of relationships in a social network. And you
could imagine that it's possible maybe you're
frenemies with someone, right? Like you don't like
them. And so maybe you have a negative weight
associated with an edge in a social network. I'm not
sure. Maybe not. But there are lots of applications
where you might want weights on your edges.
So that comes to the next
question of how do I represent,
how do I give the
user or the algorithm
these weights in my graph, right? We
had a representation for a graph, right?
Our common way to represent a graph was store a
set data structure on the vertices, mapping to the
adjacencies of each vertex, which we stored in what we called
an adjacency list, which really could be any data structure,
right?
Commonly, it's just an array of the adjacencies. But you could also
have that be a set data structure where you can query in constant
time if a particular
adjacency exists in that graph.
So a common way, there
are two kind of common ways
to store these weights. One is just with every adjacency,
I'm going to store its weight. Maybe just in a tuple,
with each adjacency,
also store
weight
of the edge that it
corresponds to, just in any way.
Instead of trying to modify our
graph structure that we gave you before,
let's just have a dictionary of all the edges mapping to
their weights, right? And we already know how to do that.
Just any set data
structure, any separate
set data structure
mapping edges to their,
I guess, weights.
Bad notation. But
you get the idea,
OK?
And it doesn't really matter how we're doing this. The assumption
that we're going to rely on here is that given an edge,
given this vertex pair,
I can query what
the weight of that edge
is in constant time, right?
And so if I'm going to do that, I can either store it with
maybe a hash table of hash tables, a hash table mapping
the set of vertices to their
adjacencies, and then each adjacency list
stores its adjacencies in a hash table. And that way, in
constant time, I can check what the weight is there. Or here,
I could even have just a single
hash table mapping the pair, the edge,
the tuple,
constant size,
to its weight, right?
So either way is fine.
We're just going to assume that we
can query an edge in constant time.
The weight of an
edge in constant time.
OK. So this is that
graph example.
It's a little busy here. I'm probably
going to erase that in just a second.
But we're going to move on to what giving these
edges weights implies for kind of these problems
that we've defined in terms of unweighted graphs, right? In particular,
we are going to be concentrating on single source shortest paths. Again,
at least for the next three lectures, we'll generalize that even
still in the next lecture. I mean, in three lectures from now.
But what we had here was that the distance before in an
unweighted graph was the number of edges in the path.
Here, we're going to
generalize that notion
kind of obviously
to weighted paths,
right?
So and the weight of a path,
I'm going to call
it pi. So weight of
path pi,
right,
is just going to be
the sum of the weights in
the edges in the path,
right? So edge in the path,
I'm going to sum
their weights, right? That's all this the weight
of a path means. It's just I'm going to sum all
the weights in a path. So if I took a look
at the maybe there's a particular path here,
the path from A to B to F to G,
right, is going to be minus 5, minus 4, 2. That's
going to be minus 9 plus 2 is minus 7, right?
OK. So just as an example.
So
then what
is the shortest path then?
Well, kind of obviously among
all paths between two vertices,
it's going to be one with
the minimum weight, right?
Yeah, question. Can I use the same edge more than
once? Can I use the same edge more than once?
Right now,
you're asking about the distinction in our class,
which we have between paths and simple paths,
right? So here, a weighted path doesn't really care if we visit an
edge more than once. Right? So if an edge appears more than once in pi,
we have to count that more than
once in the weight of the path.
OK, great question.
But what we're going
to see later on is
shortest paths
cannot repeat an
edge more than once
in certain contexts,
right? So we're going to get to the problem there a little later. In
this lecture, and we're going to solve that in tomorrow's lecture.
But if you have,
we're getting a little ahead of ourselves.
But when we have negative weights in a graph,
it's possible that things go wrong. We're
going to get there in about five lines.
OK, great.
So the shortest path,
and in this case, I'm going to clarify that
this is the weighted shortest path, right,
is a minimum,
min, mom,
short,
is a minimum weight
path from s to t, right?
Nothing too interesting here. But there's actually
some subtlety we have to deal with here, right?
We're going to call, just like we did with
breadth first search when we talked about shortest
paths, we're going to define an
expression for what the distance or
the shortest path weight is between two vertices. And that's going to, I'm
going to represent that by a delta, right? A delta from a vertex s to t
is going to be,
I'm going to do the
wrong thing first,
the minimum over the
weight of all paths
for all paths pi from
s to t.
OK,
so there's a couple of
things that go wrong here.
First thing that goes wrong is
the same thing that went wrong
with breadth first
search, right?
Anyone remember what could go wrong with breadth
first search for this delta definition? Maybe
there's no path, right?
Right, so except if no path,
just by convention,
we're
setting delta s t to equal
infinity. But there's one
additional problem
with weighted shortest paths.
And it's a little subtle.
It's possible that a finite
length shortest path doesn't exist.
And what do I mean by that? It means I could keep
going through edges in my graph and continually
getting a shorter path, right? So if I can, if the
shortest, the minimum weight of a path from s to
t actually goes through an infinite number of
edges, then this isn't really well defined, right?
So I'm going to change
this minimum here to,
in mathematics,
just to be specific, we
call it an infimum, right?
So if, in the case where the weight of a shortest path can approach
arbitrarily small, right, then we'll call this thing minus infinity, OK?
So when does that occur?
When does that occur?
When could we have our shortest path
go through lots and lots of vertices?
Let's take a look
at this example here.
Can someone tell me
what the shortest path is
from a
to actually any
vertex in this graph?
Ah,
OK.
So,
well, we could look at this path I have to b.
Let's just take a look at b, right? I have a path
going from a to b that is minus 5. OK, that's
pretty good. That's pretty small, right?
And it seems that if I go around
this graph through another way,
it might be bigger,
right? So I go 7 plus 3
plus 8. That's 15 minus 1.
That's 14. That's much bigger than minus 5. So
it seems like minus 5 should be good, right?
Anyone have a problem
with this path or a
problem with this
being the shortest path?
What just informed me was that there is something
interesting happening here in this graph. In particular,
we have a cycle
from b to f to g to c
that has negative total
weight, right, back to b, right?
This has minus 4 plus 2 plus 1 minus 1, right? So that total cycle
has a cycle weight of minus 2, right? This is a negative weight cycle.
So
if
I want to get to b, I could go
there via this minus 5 weight edge.
But every time I
circled around this cycle,
I incur minus 2 to my path weight, right? So I just keep going around
this cycle over and over and over and over and over and over again.
And I don't have
any finite length
minimum weight path,
right?
And in such cases, we just say that delta is minus infinity, right?
So the problem here is that we could have negative weight cycles.
Deserves a capital letter.
Negative weight cycles.
It's a problem,
OK? In particular,
if
there exists a path
from
s to
some vertex v that
goes through a vertex,
we're going to set
to minus infinity, OK?
And in such cases,
in our shortest paths algorithm, we don't really
care about what the shortest path is, right? We're
not even going to deal with parent pointers here,
right? Because there is no finite length shortest path.
So I'm just going to kind of throw my hands in the air and say, you know
what? I can't return you a shortest path. But I might want to return to you
a negative weight cycle, right? If you
told me that this thing has bad weight,
right, maybe I want you to tell me what a path
is that goes through a negative weight cycle
to get back to s, right? So that's what we're
going to talk about next lecture. This lecture,
we are not going to talk about that. We are going
to talk about weighted shortest paths, though.
That's what the remainder of this unit on graphs
is really about, is weighted shortest paths, OK?
So in weighted shortest paths, we actually
know an algorithm already to solve a subset
of weighted shortest
paths, namely BFS, right?
Now,
you're like, wait, Jason.
BFS doesn't solve weighted shortest paths. We didn't even know about weighted
graphs then, right? How does that solve weighted shortest paths? Well,
there's a couple
cases where we might be able to reduce to solving shortest
paths using BFS. Can anyone think of such a scenario?
So let's say, I mean, kind of what we did before
was we counted the number of edges, right?
So if we gave a weight of 1
to every edge in my graph,
then just
that graph, that weighted graph,
corresponds to an
unweighted graph using
the other distance metric,
right?
So in that case,
BFS just solves our problem. And
in fact, we can generalize further.
What if all of our weights
were positive but the same value,
right?
If it was all positive
and the same value,
then we could just
divide by that value,
right? Now we have an unweighted graph, which we can run BFS.
And then multiply shortest path distances by that value later on.
And in fact, there's one further
generalization we could make,
which is a little bit of a
tricky graph transformation problem.
But we can also get this
linear time algorithm for
weighted single source
shortest paths in contexts where
the weights aren't that large,
OK?
So if I have
positive edge weights,
right,
if I have a positive
edge weight that's, say,
using my weight color here,
that's like weight of 4, right,
that's kind of problematic because I don't know
how to simulate that using an unweighted graph.
Or do I?
Anyone have an idea of how I
could simulate an edge of weight 4?
With an unweighted graph, yeah?
I have four edges of weight 1. JASON KUOCHINASABAGIA - Yeah,
I can just put four edges of weight 1 in parallel here.
Sorry, in series,
the opposite of parallel,
OK?
I can just convert this here
into 1, 2,
3,
4 edges.
And if I do that for every edge in my
graph and we have positive edge weights,
then that transformation can hold. Now, that's not
necessarily a good transformation to make. Why?
The weight might be very big. JASON KUOCHINASABAGIA - Yeah, the weights
might be very big compared to the number of vertices and edges in my graph.
However, if the sum of all weights
in my graph is asymptotically less
than v plus e, right,
we can get a linear time algorithm again
by reducing to BFS. OK, so that's great.
Today,
but in general, that gives us a linear
time algorithm in these very special cases.
And in general, it's
an open problem. We don't
know whether we can solve the single source
shortest paths problem in the weighted context
for general graphs in linear
time. We don't know how to do it,
right? But what we do know are some algorithms that
do pretty well. And that's what we use all the time.
But in the one more special case we're going to go
over today is when we have this really nice structure
where we have a DAG,
a directed acyclic graph,
like we were talking about
in the last lecture,
we can actually, for any set of edge weights, right? Remember,
with BFS, we needed to restrict our edge weights to be positive
and maybe bounded to get
this good running time.
But
for any set of edge weights, if our graph structure is a DAG, it really
has nothing to do with the weights. If the graph structure is a DAG,
then we can actually solve this single
source shortest paths problem in linear time,
which is pretty awesome, right?
Now,
for general graphs,
we're going to show
you in the next lecture how to, for any graph,
even with cycles, even with negative weight cycles,
we're going to show you how to solve this single
source shortest paths problem in something like a
quadratic running time bound. Now, this isn't the best known, but
it's a really practical algorithm, and people use it all the time.
And we are going to show Bellman -Ford in the context
of the DAG algorithm we're going to solve today.
So that's the very general case in
terms of restrictions on our graph.
But in reality, most problems that come up in applications
occur with graphs that have positive edge weights.
You can think of a road network, or non -negative
ones anyway, right? That you're traveling along,
right? And it's not ever useful to kind of go back to where you came
from because you want to make progress to where you're going, okay?
So in the context where you don't have negative weights, you
don't have this problem where you have negative weight cycles.
We can actually do a lot better
by exploiting that property,
and we get a bound that looks a little bit more
like n log n, right? Like it's pretty close to
linear. You're losing a log
factor on the number of vertices,
okay? But it's pretty good. This is called
Dijkstra, and we'll get to that in two lectures.
Okay, so that's kind of the roadmap of what
we're going to do for the next three lectures.
But before we go on to
showing you how to solve
single source shortest paths in a DAG using this
algorithm that I'm calling DAG relaxation here,
I'm going to go back to a thing that we talked
about in breadth -first search, where in breadth
-first search, when we solve
single source shortest paths,
we output two things, right? We output
single source shortest paths these deltas,
right, for the other definition of distance, you know,
the weights. I mean, not the weights, the distances,
the shortest distances.
But we also return parent pointers,
right? We return parent pointers back
along paths to the source
along shortest paths, right? We
call this the shortest paths tree.
So I'm going to revisit this topic of
shortest paths tree, shortest path trees.
Shortest path trees,
okay?
And in particular,
it's kind of going
to be annoying
to talk about both
of these quantities,
right, distances and parent pointers, as we go
through all three of these algorithms, right? It's
basically going to be bookkeeping to distances are
actually sufficient for us to reconstruct parent
pointers if we need them later. Okay? So what I'm going to show for
you, prove to you now, is that if I give you the shortest path distances
for the subset of the
graph reachable from S
that doesn't go through
negative weight cycles,
right,
if I'm giving you those
distances, I can reconstruct
parent pointers along
shortest paths in linear time
for any graph I might give you if I
give you those shortest paths. Okay.
So that's what I'm
going to try to show to
you now.
So here's the algorithm.
For weighted,
there's the caveat here
I'm going to write down.
For
weighted shortest paths,
only need
parent pointers for v
with finite shortest
path distance.
Okay?
Only finite shortest path distance, right? We
don't care about the infinite ones or the minus
infinite ones, just the finite
ones. Okay. So here's the algorithm.
I'm going to initialize
all pv to equal
sorry.
Oh.
Getting ahead of myself.
I'm writing down dag.
All right.
Init all,
init my parent pointer
data structure, right,
to be empty.
Okay? Right? First, I'm not
going to store any parent pointers,
but at the beginning,
I'm going to set the parent pointer
of the source to be empty. None.
Right? So that's what we kind of did
in breadth first search as well. Right?
Now,
what I've given you is I'm trying to show that given all the shortest
path distances, I can construct these parent pointers correctly.
So what I'm going
to do is for each
vertex u in my graph where
my delta
s of u is finite,
what
am I going to do? I'm going
to say, well,
let's take a look at
all my outgoing neighbors.
Okay? This is kind of what
we do in every graph algorithm.
For each v in the adjacency,
the outgoing adjacencies of
u,
if
there is no parent
pointer assigned to this v,
right,
there's the potential that I, u, I, u, this u, this vertex u, is
the parent of v. It's possible. Right? It's some incoming edge to v.
Okay?
When will it be an
incoming edge to v?
If I haven't said if,
v not in p. Right? I haven't
assigned it a parent pointer.
And so this means it could
be my parent.
When is it my parent?
Along the shortest path.
Sure. Yeah.
So we have some
edge from u to v.
It has some weight. Right?
If I already know the shortest path distance to
u, and I know the shortest path distance to v,
right,
if
the shortest path distance from s to u, let's draw a picture here. We've
got s. We've got some path here to u. And we've got an edge from u to v.
Okay?
If this shortest path distance
across this edge weight is equal to
the shortest path distance from s to v,
then it better be, I mean, there may be more
than one shortest path, but this is certainly a
shortest path. So we can assign a parent pointer back
to u. Okay? Right? So let's write that condition down.
If the shortest path distance from s to v
equals the shortest path distance from s to u,
and then traversing
the edge from u to v,
then exists shortest path
that
uses
edge u of v.
Right?
In particular, this one.
So set the parent of u
of v to u.
Okay.
So this is the algorithm. I'm not going
to prove to you that this is correct,
but it kind of intuitively
makes sense. Right? If I have
these shortest path distances,
right, you can prove by induction that not only
does this parent pointer point to the right place
along some shortest path here. Right? But it also
does so in linear time because I'm looping over
all the vertices and looping over
its outgoing and adjacencies once.
Same analysis as we had for
both BFS and DFS, essentially.
Right?
And then, since we can do this, since we can compute parent
pointers from these distances, we're going to kind of ignore
computing these parent
pointers from now on.
Right? We're just going to concentrate on computing the distances
because, you know, we're going to have to take linear time anyway.
Right? At least.
And all these other
things take more time.
So we can compute the distances in more
time and then compute the parents after.
Okay.
So that's what
we're going to do.
Okay. So now, with all that
buildup, let's show an algorithm.
Right? How do
we compute shortest,
single source
shortest paths in a DAG
in linear time?
Okay.
Well, a DAG, I mean, this is actually a super
useful, convenient thing in algorithms in general.
DAGs are just nice things. Right? They're kind of
ordered in a way. Right? There's this topological
sort order that we were talking about
before. This is going to play a key role.
Right? There's a really nice structure to DAGs
not having cycles, not having to deal with this
negative weight cycle problem. Right? You can
only kind of go in one direction along this graph.
Right?
It's a very nice structure to exploit.
And so we're going to exploit it.
And here's the idea.
DAG relaxation,
what it's going to do is it's going to start out with
some estimates of what these distances should be. Right?
Okay. So
maintain distance estimates.
And now, I'm going to try to be
careful here about how I draw my d's.
Okay. This is a d.
This is a delta.
Okay.
This is shortest paths.
This is a distance estimate.
Okay. So that's what I'm going to
be using for the rest of this time.
So we're going to initialize,
maintain these estimates of distance d, which
are going to start at initially infinite.
Right?
Okay. I don't know what they are. Right? I don't know what
the shortest paths are. But they better be less than infinite
or else I don't care. Right? So I'm going to, that's the kind of worst
case scenario. Right? It can't be worse than this for every vertex.
And we're going to maintain
the property that estimates
that
the upper bound, that
should probably be two words,
upper bound delta sv.
We're going to maintain that the upper
bound this thing and gradually lower until
they're equal.
Okay? So this is the
idea. We start from
an overestimate, an upper
bound on the distance estimate.
And then we're repeatedly going to lower that
value as we gain more information about the graph.
Maintaining that we're always
upper bounding the distance.
And we're going to keep doing it, keep doing it,
keep doing it until, as we will try to prove to you,
these estimates reach, actually reach down
all the way to our shortest path distances.
Okay?
So when do we
lower these things?
When do we lower these things?
We're going to lower these distance estimates whenever the distance
estimates violate what we're going to call the triangle inequality.
Okay. What is the
triangle inequality?
Triangle inequality is actually
a pretty intuitive notion.
Okay?
It's basically saying if I have
three points, that's this triangle.
Right?
Maybe bigger so I can
write a letter in them.
Okay. It's basically saying
that if I have a vertex u,
a vertex v,
vertex x, for example. Right?
The shortest path distance
delta of u, v.
That's the shortest path distance from u to v. It can't be
bigger than a shortest path from u to v that also goes through x.
Right?
Right? Of my paths, I'm now restricting the
paths that I have to the ones that go through x.
Right?
The shortest path distance from u to v can't be bigger than
restricting paths that go through x and taking that shortest distance.
Right? Getting the shortest path distance from here
and adding it to the shortest path distance here.
Right?
Delta u, x.
Delta x, v.
Right?
I mean,
that's just a statement of I'm restricting to a
subset of the paths. I can't increase my, I can't
decrease my minimum distance. Right? So this
is the statement of the triangle inequality.
Right? That the shortest
path distance from u to v is,
can't be bigger than the
shortest path distance from u to x
plus the shortest path
distance from x to v
for any x in my graph
that's not u and v. Okay?
So that's the
triangle inequality.
Pretty intuitive notion. Right?
Okay. Why is this useful?
Okay. Well, if I find,
if I find an edge in my graph,
if there's an edge u,
v in my graph, such that
this condition is violated for the estimates that I have. Right?
It obviously can't be violated on my shortest path distances.
On the estimates,
u, v is bigger than u,
x.
Sorry. U, how
am I going to do this?
I want this to be s.
I'm calculating shortest
path distances from s.
And shortest path distances from s to
some incoming vertex u plus the edge weight
from u
to v.
Okay?
All right. So
what is this doing?
I have some edge
u, v in my graph.
Okay?
Basically what I've said is that
I have some distance estimate to u,
but
going through, making a
path to v by going through u,
and then the edge from u to v
is better
than my current estimate,
my shortest path estimate
to v.
That's bad. Right? That's violating the triangle
inequality. These cannot be the right weights.
Right? These cannot
be the right distances.
So how we're going to do that is lower. This is what
we said repeatedly lower these distance estimates.
I'm going to lower this
guy down to equal this thing.
In a sense, this constraint was violated. But now we're
relaxing that constraint so that this is no longer violated.
Right?
So that's, I'm, I'm,
relax is a little weird word here. We're using it
for historical reasons, but that's what we mean
by when we say relax. This
thing is a violated constraint.
It's got some pressure
to be resolved.
Right? And so what we're doing is to resolve it,
we're just setting this guy equal to this. So it
at least resolves locally that constraint. Now it
may violate the triangle inequality other where
else, other places. Now that we've done this change, but at
least this constraint is now relaxed and satisfied. Okay. So,
we're going to relax
edge by lowering
d of sv to this thing.
Okay? That's what we're going
to mean by relaxing an edge.
Okay?
And relaxing an edge
is what I'll call safe.
It's safe to do. Okay?
What
do I mean by relaxation
is safe? It means
that as I am computing these shortest path
distances, right? I'm going to maintain this property
that each one of these estimates, sorry, these estimates here has the
property that it's either infinite or it is the weight of some path to v.
Okay?
So that's, that's the thing
that relaxation is safe.
Okay.
So each distance
estimate sv is weight
of some path
from s to v or infinite.
Okay?
And this is a pretty
easy thing to prove. Right?
If I had the invariant that
these were all weights of shortest
paths, let's try to relax an edge.
Right?
And we need to show that
this property is maintained.
Relax edge uv.
Okay?
Now if I relax edge uv,
what do I do?
I set this thing or,
sorry, I set this thing, my
shortest path distance to v,
to be this thing
plus this thing.
Right? This is a weight
of an edge from u to v.
Now, by my assumption that
we're maintaining that this is a,
the weight of some
path in my graph,
right?
If this thing is bigger,
I'm setting it to the weight of some path. Weight of some path in
my graph to u plus an edge from u to v. And so this checks out.
So assign d of s to v
to weight of some path.
Okay? I'm not going to write down all the, all
the argument that I just had here, but basically
since this distance estimate
was by supposition before
the weight of some
path to v, to u,
right? Then this is again the
weight of some path to v. Okay. Great.
So now we're ready to actually
go through this algorithm.
So dag relaxation
from over there initializes
all of our distance estimates to
equal infinity, just like we did in BFS.
Then set
my distance estimate to
myself to be zero. Right?
Now it's possible that this might be
minus infinity or negative at some point,
but right now I'm
just setting it to zero.
Okay? And either way, zero is going
to upper bound the distance to s. Right?
So in particular,
at initialization,
anything not reachable
from s is set correctly.
And s itself is
set as an upper bound to a shortest path
distance. Okay? Now we're going to process each
vertex u in a topological
sort order.
So remember our input to
dag relaxation is a dag.
So this thing has a
topological sort order.
We're going to process
these vertices in that order.
Okay? You can imagine we're starting at the top
and all my vertices are, all my edges are pointed
away from me. And I'm just processing each
vertex down this topological sort line.
Okay?
And then for each
of these vertices,
what am I going to do? I'm going to look at all the outgoing
neighbors. And if the triangle inequality is violated,
I'm going to relax that edge.
The algorithm is
as simple as that.
For each
outgoing neighbor,
I'm going to
set a value of v,
sorry, of u.
I always get u and
v mixed up here.
Okay?
If
my shortest path estimate to v
violates the triangle inequality
for an edge, for
an incoming edge,
then I'm going to set,
relax uv,
i .e.
set dsv equal to dsu plus wuv.
Okay? So that's the algorithm.
So if
I were to take a look at
this example graph over here,
vertex,
I initialize it to,
this
is not a dag. Thank you.
Let's make it a dag.
I claim to you,
now this is a dag.
Okay? In particular, a
topological sort order is
when there's a path
through all the vertices,
then there's a unique
topological sort order, a, b, e, f,
g, h, d, c.
This is a topological order.
You can check all the edges.
So I'm going to
start by setting the,
actually, let's
use e.
Let's do shortest
paths from e. Why not?
Okay? Shortest paths from e.
Vertex a actually
comes before e.
In the topological order.
Right? So it has no, I mean, its shortest path distance
when I initialize, I'm going to initialize this to zero.
I'm going to initialize
this to infinite.
Infinite.
All these things to infinite.
These are my estimates.
These are not quite
the shortest paths yet.
Distances.
But when I get here,
clearly, I can't be,
distance to me being infinite
can never violate the triangle inequality with
something infinite or finite. Doesn't matter.
Right?
So I don't do anything to a.
Anything before my source vertex in the
topological order can't be visited. Right?
Because it's before in the topological order. That's
the kind of the point. There's no path from my
source vertex to anything
before it in the topological order.
Okay?
So,
same with b. b is before
it in the topological order.
Okay?
Now,
I'm at e.
And it's possible we are violating triangle
inequality. In particular here. Right?
I think the shortest path distance to f
is infinite. But actually, if I go to e
through this edge
with a weight three,
I know that this is violating triangle
inequality. So actually, this thing is wrong.
And I can set it equal to three.
Okay? Now, that might not
be the shortest path distance.
But right now, it's
a better estimate.
Right? So we've set it.
Okay. Now,
I'm moving on. I'm
done with this guy.
I move to the next vertex in my topological
order. And again, I relax the edges
out of f.
Okay. So here,
looking at a, eight,
three plus eight is
better than infinite.
So we'll say that that's 11.
And three plus two is better
than infinite. So that's five.
Okay? Now, I keep going in the
topological order. g is the next.
Five plus one is six. Okay. So
we found a better estimate here.
Right? So this 11 is not as good.
Six is better. So we replace it.
Here,
we haven't visited b. Before, it's still
infinite. So five plus minus two is three.
Okay?
This is the next in the topological order. Three plus
nine is bigger than six. So that's not a shorter path.
Three plus four is certainly smaller than infinite. So set that
equal to seven. Then seven plus five is also bigger than six.
And actually, you can confirm that these
are all the shortest path distances from e.
Okay? So this
algorithm seems to work.
Does it actually work?
Let's take a look.
The claim to you is
that at the end of relaxation,
this algorithm,
we've set
claim at end.
All the estimates equal
shortest path distances.
Okay?
The basic idea here
is that if I take
the k -th vertex in
the topological order,
assuming that these
distances are all equal
for the ones before me
in the topological order,
I can prove by induction. Right?
So I can take the
shortest path from s to v.
Right? The k -th vertex.
And look at the vertex preceding me
along the shortest path. Right? That
vertex better
be before me in the topological
order, or we're not a DAG.
Right?
And we've already set its
shortest path distance to be equal
to the correct
thing by induction.
So then when we
processed u, right?
S to u to v.
When we processed u
in DAG relaxation here,
processed the vertex and looked
at all its outgoing adjacencies,
we would have relaxed this edge to be no
greater than that shortest path distance.
So this is correct. But
you can also think of it
as the DAG relaxation algorithm for each
vertex looks all at its incoming neighbors,
assuming that their shortest path
distances are computed correctly already.
Right? Any shortest path distance to me needs to be composed
of a shortest path distance to one of my incoming neighbors
through an edge to me.
So I can just check all of them.
That's what DAG
relaxation kind of does.
And again,
we're looping over every vertex and looking
at its adjacencies, doing constant work.
This again takes linear time.
OK. So that's shortest
paths in a DAG.
Next time, we'll look at, for general graphs,
how we can use kind of the same technique
in an algorithm we
call Bellman -Ford. OK.
That's it for today.